<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A serman preached at Manchester, upon the 9th of September, being the day of thanksgiving for our deliverance from the late conspiracy</title>
            <author>Foreness, E.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39968</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11966635</idno>
  <idno type="VID">51733</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264209742</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1554</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6667</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11966635</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39968)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51733)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 815:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A serman preached at Manchester, upon the 9th of September, being the day of thanksgiving for our deliverance from the late conspiracy</title>
                  <author>Foreness, E.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Miles Flesher, for William Abbington ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans XIII, 2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51733:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51733:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at MANCHESTER, Upon the 9<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>September,</hi> Being the <hi>Day of Thanksgiving</hi> For our Deliverance from the Late Conspiracy.</p>
            <p>By <hi>E. FORENESS,</hi> Presbyter of the Church of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Miles Flesher,</hi> for <hi>William Abbington,</hi> near <hi>Ludgate,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51733:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51733:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Inhabitants of <hi>MANCHESTER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT was the desire of several of you, that this <hi>Sermon</hi> should be printed, a desire I could not well deny: The <hi>Attention,</hi> that was given when I spoke; and the general <hi>Approbation</hi> afterwards of <hi>what</hi> I spoke, made me hope that my <hi>Sermon</hi> did in some measure an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer my design, which was not to <hi>revile</hi> but <hi>reason</hi> men into <hi>Honest and Loyal Principles:</hi> for which purpose I have since added some <hi>enlargements,</hi> particularly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Original and Divinity of Government:</hi> not as if I would insinuate any thing against <hi>you,</hi> or had the least intention of fixing an <hi>Odium</hi> upon that <hi>place,</hi> wherein I had a considerable part of my <hi>Education,</hi> and near to which I had my <hi>Birth:</hi> but hope, that whatever <hi>malignity</hi> the <hi>factious Ascendent</hi> of this age may have let fall amongst you, it has <hi>infected</hi> but a <hi>few;</hi> and that your <hi>LOYALTY</hi> will for ever remain <hi>UNSHA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KEN,</hi> and stand as <hi>firm</hi> as the <hi>Rock</hi> upon which your <hi>Town</hi> is <hi>Built.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Government</hi> you live under, is of God, <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Divine:</hi> it is agreeable to the <hi>Fundamental Laws</hi> of this Nation; and no other form was ever known amongst us, except in the late times of <hi>bloud</hi> and <hi>Confusion:</hi> and yet we have had, and its well if we have not still such, who would subvert and undermine it, men of <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent unquiet</hi> Spirits, who if they have not their wills, would prove as <hi>factious</hi> and <hi>uneasie</hi> under <hi>any</hi> sort of <hi>Government,</hi> as under <hi>this</hi> of a <hi>Monarchy.</hi> And these are they who generally seem to be the deeplyest concern'd for the security of our <hi>Religion:</hi> The <hi>Protestant Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest</hi> is pretended, and it may be some of them are in good
<pb facs="tcp:51733:3"/> earnest. But believe me, Sirs, there are other <hi>Emis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries</hi> besides those from <hi>Rome,</hi> and that <hi>altogether</hi> as busie and dangerous, and of which you ought to be <hi>alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether</hi> as carefull; they will take the advantage of your <hi>Religious Inclinations,</hi> and insensibly betray you into ill Opinions and thoughts of things. For give me leave to tell you, that there is no <hi>Temptation</hi> more prevailing and dangerous, than the <hi>Insinuations</hi> of <hi>men of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi> An honest minded man is the soonest ensnar'd by such he takes to be honest and pious. The greatest <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks</hi> (setting aside the <hi>Gnosticks</hi> of the primitive times) were men of great Piety and Zeal, and by that means gain'd so many Proselytes and followers; to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance onely in one of our own Island, viz. <hi>Pelagius,</hi> he was a man of unblemisht Piety and Devotion, and by that means as well as by his Learning and pretences of Reason, infected not onely <hi>Britain,</hi> but a great part of the <hi>Christian world,</hi> with that pernicious Heresie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>Divine Grace</hi> and <hi>Assistance.</hi> I onely men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this, that you should not have mens persons in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, nor suffer your selves to be imposed upon, either in reference to <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> by any man whatever, however Holy or Strict he may appear in his Life and Conversation, but prove the Spirits, try all Things, and hold fast that which is good. In fine, study to be quiet, and do your own business, <hi>Fear the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change. For their Calamity shall rise suddenly, and who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Ruine of them both,</hi> (Prov. <hi>24.21, 22.</hi>)</p>
            <closer>May Almighty God give a blessing to this small imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect piece, and make it usefull and serviceable to you, and I do assure you, the whole design is answer'd, of Sirs,
<signed>your true, unfeigned Friend, <hi>E. Foreness.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51733:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 13.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Whosoever therefore resisteth the Power, resisteth the ordinance of God, and they that resist shall receive to themselves damnation.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THere is scarce any thing has occasion'd more hatred to the <hi>orthodox Clergy</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> than their frequent preaching up Submission to Government, and to <hi>Our Government</hi> as by Law establisht both in Church and State; an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument one would think, could never be unwelcome to such as lov'd their King, and the peace of their Country, nor be thought unseasonable by any, who have but in the least taken notice how boldly men of late talk'd and printed too all the old principles of <hi>DISLOYALTY</hi> and <hi>REBELLION.</hi> It was sure high time to press obedience in the Pulpit, when there was so little in our practice, and the Generality were grown so insolent, that <hi>to be offended with the Government,</hi> was an Argument of a <hi>good Patriot,</hi> and they were the most acceptable to the people, who were the most obnoxious to their Governours; when <hi>FACTION</hi> roll'd up and down the Kingdom with a train por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending more dire Effects than the longest blaze of the most prodigious Comet, and became so potent and formidable, that had not that God who <hi>stilleth the noise of the Seas, stilled also the Tumult of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> This day instead of being a <hi>Festival,</hi> a day of Thanks, Joy and Rejoycing, might have been a day
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51733:4"/> of <hi>Confusion,</hi> a day of Sorrow, Mourning and Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. But for ever blessed be our God, who hath disperst the Clouds that were gathering over us, and caus'd the Light of his Countenance to shine upon us. He hath defeated the machinations and deliver'd us from the designs of these men; He hath once more socur'd the Throne and Life of our Sovereign, and by this his gratious providence hath signaliz'd his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for <hi>Authority,</hi> and opposition to <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Resistence. Whosoever therefore resisteth the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>There are some especial times wherein men are more capable of Instruction, and Receptive of Truth than others, and my hopes are, that this may be one of those times; The present Circumstances in which our Nation is, may by the blessing of God have this good effect, as to be a means to open our Eyes, and let in that Light, which we have hitherto resisted.</p>
            <p>I shall therefore make use of this opportunity to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present unto you,</p>
            <p>First of all, The Original and Divinity of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> it is from God, His Ordinance.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Explain to you this Doctrine of <hi>Non-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance,</hi> and,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Shew you the ill Consequences of the contrary Doctrine of <hi>Resisting the power. Whosoever resisteth the power, resisteth the Ordinance of God, and they that resist (WHOSOEVER THEY BE, and ƲN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER WHAT PRETENCE SOEVER) shall receive to themselves damnation.</hi> But,</p>
            <p>First, Of the Original and Divinity of <hi>Government, He that resisteth the power, resisteth the Ordinance of God:</hi> By <hi>power</hi> here is meant Empire, Magistracy and Dominion, and connotes the person or persons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vested therewith; This power, which is in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51733:4"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is distinguisht from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> signifying bare force and might, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a just Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy or Government, and of this we are to treat; and if we look backwards to the first Rise of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we shall find it to be as ancient as the World, nay more ancient, if we will believe what some if not most of the <hi>Greek</hi> Fathers have asserted, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Angels were created long before the World, who certainly were under the Command and Government of God their great Creatour. But not to meddle with this Kingdom of Spirits; Let us consider the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of Visible and Earthly Sovereignty, and this was in Paradise it self, that wherein God invested Man as soon as he was created. He was made Sovereign of the World, and all things therein were subjected to his Dominion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. He was constituted sole Lord and Proprietour of all, and all the right that accru'd afterwards to others was by <hi>Donation</hi> or <hi>Cession.</hi> Man indeed being created single, and there being as yet no other persons besides <hi>Adam,</hi> his Authority could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend no farther than to these inferiour Creatures; but as soon as God had made the woman, he brought her to the man, and gave her to him, and he in token of her Subjection imposeth a name upon her, <hi>viz.</hi> that of <hi>Woman,</hi> imposing of Names being an Argument of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; so that from that very time there were any persons capable of being govern'd, there has been a Government. Mankind was distinguisht not onely by <hi>Sex</hi> but by <hi>Power,</hi> which at first could be no larger than a private Family, but still as their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers encreas'd, so did the <hi>power</hi> of their Prince, which was <hi>Adam</hi> during his Life, and afterwards <hi>Seth</hi> and so on, the first-born of every Family being as <hi>Jacob</hi> styles <hi>Reuben,</hi> the <hi>excellency of Dignity,</hi> and <hi>the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of power,</hi> the Supreme Governour over the rest;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51733:5"/> and this right of <hi>Primogeniture</hi> is founded or acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd in <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.7. where God tells <hi>Cain</hi> concerning <hi>Abel, Ʋnto thee,</hi> says he, <hi>shall be his desire, and thou shalt rule over him.</hi> Whether God did here positively institute this Superiority of the <hi>first-born,</hi> or onely recognize that right and title which he had by <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> is not much material to determine, though this last seems to me most probable, God hereby telling <hi>Cain,</hi> that though <hi>Abel</hi>'s offering was more acceptable than his, yet this should not any way abate of his <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural prerogative and Authority,</hi> but still <hi>Abel</hi> should be subject to him, and he should rule over him. God has indeed sometimes inverted this Order, and made the Elder to serve the Younger, but this is no Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that we should; it being a case particularly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd to God, the principles of <hi>Nature</hi> telling us that the <hi>first-born</hi> should have privileges over and above the <hi>younger:</hi> and from this I date the Original of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: It was <hi>Patriarchal,</hi> founded in the very <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> which is the very Law of God, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that unwritten Law, whereby God did at first mostly govern the World.</p>
            <p>Mankind was never without some sort of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> or other, for indeed it could never have subsisted without it; in the most Savage and Barbarous Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, there was still some kind of <hi>Superiority and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency,</hi> though broken and confus'd.</p>
            <p>And according to this Natural institution of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> God hath expresly appear'd in it by his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. We are told, <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.5. <hi>By these were the Isles of the Gentiles divided in their Lands, every one after their Tongue, after their Families in their Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> Learned men from hence conjecture, and that not without Reason, that the world was divided not by <hi>chance</hi> but by an especial <hi>Providence;</hi> it was regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51733:5"/> parted amongst the Sons of <hi>Noah,</hi> and the busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness was so order'd, that particular Countries were divided out to such particular Families, as had such and such particular Languages.<note n="*" place="margin">f. <hi>9.</hi> as he is quoted.</note>
               <hi>Cedrenus</hi> tells us, that <hi>Noah</hi> divided the World amongst his three Sons <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by some <hi>divine Oracle</hi> or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation;</hi> but whether it were so or no, no doubt but the <hi>providence</hi> of God was much concern'd in it; Mankind growing so numerous as that they could not well be under the Government of one, they were divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and subdivided into several parts and districts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their several Kings and Princes. Having thus given you an account of the Original of <hi>Government,</hi> that it is founded in <hi>Nature;</hi> Superiority and Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority, Authority and Subjection, being Relations as Natural as High and Low, as Great and Small; it follows that it must be from God (the <hi>Law of Nature</hi> being no other than the <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Appointment of God;</hi>) as will more fully appear if we consider the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations God has been pleas'd to make concerning this matter in the Scriptures. In them Magistrates are styl'd <hi>Gods</hi> and <hi>the Sons of God,</hi> they mostly resembling God in their <hi>power</hi> and <hi>Majesty,</hi> and being the next in order to him of any of these visible Beings in the World. It is a saying amongst the <hi>Arabians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Christoph. Arnold. Ep. Ded. <hi>prefixt to</hi> Rupertus <hi>his</hi> Historia Universalis.</note> that <hi>the King is the shadow of God,</hi> and he is certainly the nearest similitude of him, and does the most illustri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously represent him of any sublunary Creature. A principal part, of the Image of God consists in <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> as God is an Universal Governour, so Kings and Princes are particular subordinate Governours under him and for him; hence the <hi>Throne of the King</hi> is said to be the <hi>Throne of God,</hi> and they are said to be <hi>his Kings</hi> and <hi>his Anointed; By me</hi> (says the Wisedom of God) <hi>Kings reign, and Princes decree Justice,</hi> Prov. 8, 15,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51733:6"/> and our Saviour tells us, <hi>John</hi> 10.35. that they <hi>were called Gods, because unto them the word of God came, i. e.</hi> it was his Appointment and Commandment that they should rule in his name and in his room.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Usher,</hi> Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Prince.</note> But a more full account of the mind of God we cannot well have, than what this 13th. chapter of the <hi>Romans</hi> does afford us, we are told in as full and plain words as can be, that <hi>the powers that be are ordain'd of God, and that he that resisteth the power resisteth the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God,</hi> and in the 6th. <hi>v.</hi> the Magistrates are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>the Ministers of God,</hi> and it has been observ'd that this word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, at least the <hi>N. T.</hi> never attributed to any but such as have some sacred function either immediately instituted and prescribed by God himself, or in its own nature agreeable to his will.</p>
            <p>All this it may be will be confest, it being acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd by most, that <hi>Government</hi> in general is from God, of divine Appointment and Institution, but the great dispute is about the <hi>Specification</hi> thereof, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any <hi>particular form</hi> be an ordinance of God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusively to others: there are those who deny it, and assert that though <hi>Government in Thesi</hi> be of God, yet the choice of a <hi>particular form</hi> is of man, no more than a Humane Ordinance; that it is indifferent by the Laws of God, whether we set up this or that <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular form.</hi> It may be look'd upon as presumption to condemn all other forms of <hi>Government</hi> as sinfull and wicked, yet this I shall venture to say, that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> puts in the fairest plea's of any to be <hi>Juris Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vini</hi> of Divine Right, and that exclusively to all the rest, for to me it is certain,</p>
            <p>First of all, That this is the most <hi>natural</hi> and <hi>anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> way of Government in the World,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Clem. l.</hi> 1. cap. 19.</note>
               <hi>Natura com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta est Regem,</hi> says <hi>Seneca,</hi> a King is the Invention and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51733:6"/> dictate of Nature it self, and was indeed the first sort of Goverment that was ever in use either in Heaven or Earth. This might be prov'd by various quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but they are needless, it being in a manner confest, that no other sort of Government did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail in the world for the first three thousand years, but <hi>Monarchy.</hi> Other ways and forms were chiefly owing to the <hi>Grecians,</hi> a volatile, unstable and giddy sort of people. In the <hi>East,</hi> those parts, where the world was first inhabited, they were all along go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Monarches,</hi> and so are to this day, a strong presumption that the <hi>first</hi> Government of the world and the <hi>most natural</hi> is the Regal or King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. But</p>
            <p>Secondly, It may be farther observ'd, that there is in Scripture no command (at least exprest) to obey any other form of Government than <hi>that of Kings,</hi> nor is there any other form of Government mention'd or taken notice of unless you will except that of the <hi>Gibeonites.</hi> It is to Kings that we are to be subject, <hi>Fear the Lord and the King,</hi> says the Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.21. and St. <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts to <hi>submit our selves to every Ordinance of man for the Lord's sake, whether it be to the King as Supreme, or unto Governours as unto them that are sent by him,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet,</hi> 2.13. Neither our Saviour, nor any of his Apostles, nor any of the primitive Fathers, that ever I heard of, did fault the Government of their times, which was <hi>Despotical</hi> and <hi>Monarchical,</hi> but oblige all to obedience and submission.</p>
            <p>One of the greatest objections against this privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege and advantage of Kingly Government, is the account we have in <hi>Samuel,</hi> chap. 8. how that God was angry with the <hi>Israelites</hi> for demanding of a King, which supposes, First that they were not go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51733:7"/> by Kings before; And Secondly, That when God did give them a King it was in Anger, it was a Judgment, no mercy. As to the first I answer, that the <hi>Jewish</hi> Government was a <hi>Theocracy,</hi> it was God himself that fought their Battels, gave them their Laws, and in all emergent difficulties, appointed what was to be done, so that he was their <hi>proper King</hi> and <hi>especial Governour;</hi> the <hi>Judges,</hi> or the <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrim,</hi> acted onely as Deputies under him. But we may answer farther, that before <hi>Saul</hi> was made King, the name of <hi>King</hi> was not in use, but that of <hi>Judges,</hi> yet those <hi>Judges</hi> had <hi>Regal power,</hi> and were in their respective times under God <hi>Supreme Governours</hi> of the <hi>Jewish</hi> Nation; and the form of their Government even in those days,<note place="margin">Quaenam erat reipub. forma sub Judicibus? <hi>Resp.</hi> Monarchica. Synops. Crit. in lib. Jud. ad init.</note>
               <hi>when there was no King in Israel,</hi> was <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical.</hi> And as to the Second, God's being angry with them for demanding a King; It is very true he was so, and he had reason to be so; not as if the thing had been absolutely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull or inconvenient, for God Almighty himself gave orders to them about chusing of a King, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.14, 15. but their fault in this particular case seems to me to have been <hi>their demanding of a King at this time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that God had set <hi>Samuel</hi> over them, he was in a peculiar way appointed by God to be their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, so that in rejecting him, they rejected the Authority of God; Had <hi>Samuel</hi> been dead and the <hi>Government vacant,</hi> I am apt to think, there would have been no sin in demanding a King, whereas now, as the case stood, whilst <hi>Samuel</hi> was alive, to depose him (which in effect they did by demanding a King,) was to contemn that Authority, which had set him over them; and upon this account, God
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51733:7"/> might well be angry with them, and <hi>give them a King in his wrath,</hi> that is, such a King as should be a plague and punishment to them.</p>
            <p>All these things consider'd, they are not so much to be blam'd and look'd upon as <hi>Court-Parasites,</hi> who assert <hi>Monarchy</hi> exclusively to all other sorts of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to be <hi>Jure Divino.</hi> There are those who would fain perswade the world, that there are none but a few of the <hi>younger</hi> and <hi>meaner</hi> sort of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> such as <hi>frequent publick Houses, and want the Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their preferments,</hi> that are of this opinion; whereas it has been declar'd by a <hi>whole Convocation,</hi> Anno 1640.<note place="margin">Constitut. and Can. Ecclesias<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical. <hi>A. 1640.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>That the most High and Sacred order of Kings is of Divine Right, being the ordinance of God himself, founded in the prime Laws of Nature, and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly establisht by express texts both of the Old and New Testament, and that a Supreme power is given to this most excellent order by God himself in Scriptures.</hi> This was the Declaration of our <hi>Bishops,</hi> and as we have reason to believe, the <hi>learnedst</hi> and <hi>gravest</hi> of our <hi>Divines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But supposing this sort of Government could plead no greater Authority than the other, yet to us under our Circumstances, to oppose it is the same, as to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the Authority of God, it being <hi>the Government of our Nation,</hi> approv'd of God by so long a Successi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and we being under the obligation of our <hi>Laws,</hi> and of those <hi>Oaths,</hi> whereby we have after the most solemn manner engag'd our Souls to God, for the maintenance and preservation thereof, so that he that resisteth <hi>this power,</hi> resisteth <hi>the ordinance of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From what has already been discourst we may infer,</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:51733:8"/>
            <p>First, <hi>That Kingly Government is no Ʋsurpation on the prerogative of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That Kings derive not their power from the people;</hi> and therefore</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>There can be no Escheat or forfeiture of the power to the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, <hi>That Kingly Government is no Ʋsurpation on the prerogative of Christ.</hi> One might have imagin'd it impossible for any one that reads the Scriptures with a design to understand them, to have thought other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, and yet there have been those, and that in great numbers, who have upon this account, <hi>viz.</hi> its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>consistency with <hi>the Royal prerogative of Christ,</hi> cry'd down and oppos'd all <hi>Magistracy.</hi> Of this sort were the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> who taking hold of some loose unwary expressions of <hi>Luther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Spanhem.</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atribe Histor. de Ortu, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Anabapt.</note> in his book of <hi>Christian Liberty,</hi> thought themselves exempted from all <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Secular</hi> as well as <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> Power and Jurisdiction; And of the same opinion there have been some amongst our selves, who would have no <hi>King,</hi> but <hi>King Jesus,</hi> follow no <hi>Banner</hi> but that of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> and damn'd all <hi>Magistracy</hi> as <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>Antichristian;</hi> as if our Religion did supersede the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of Government and Obedience, and our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our had banisht all power and Authority out of the world; whereas there is nothing so plain, as that he intermeddles no farther in these matters, than to tye the bond of obedience the <hi>faster</hi> upon us: He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to give unto <hi>Caesar</hi> the things that are <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sar</hi>'s, as well as unto <hi>God</hi> the things that are <hi>God</hi>'s; he appears before the Judgment-Seat of <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> submits to the sentence, and dyes an accursed and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious death. His <hi>Apostles</hi> were mighty carefull to tread in his steps, and give no offence to those in Authority, and therefore submitted themselves, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51733:8"/> exhort all to Submission even to the <hi>greatest Tyrants.</hi> Had the <hi>Magistracy</hi> been an <hi>Ʋsurpation</hi> on the <hi>prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative</hi> of their <hi>Master,</hi> they would never have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd his cause by silence, much more have counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanc'd the Invasion of it, by encouraging all to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Magistracy, and that <hi>for the Lord's sake;</hi> they would never sure have told as they do here in the Text, that the <hi>power was the ordinance of God,</hi> and <hi>that they that resist, should receive to themselves damnation.</hi> Our Saviour indeed was a <hi>King,</hi> and had <hi>all power</hi> given to him <hi>in Heaven and in Earth,</hi> but then <hi>his Kingdom,</hi> as he himself tells us, was <hi>not of this world.</hi> He was to reign in the minds and Souls of men; His power was to exert it self, not so much in <hi>external pomp and Empire,</hi> as in the <hi>Internal sway and Government</hi> of the Spirits of mankind; so that by this his Spiritual Kingdom, he does not invade the office of the civil Magistrate, nor take the power out of his hand, but left and continu'd him in the same State he found him.</p>
            <p>Nor by the way, does our Saviour's <hi>Spiritual Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> exclude the <hi>Magistrate</hi> from intermedling even in <hi>Spiritual Concerns,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide <hi>Kid</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> Speeches.</note> as some of the next Country have pretended. The making good Laws for the esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment and preservation of Religion, and the see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them put in Execution, is no encroachment upon our Saviour's Spiritual power and Authority; for the <hi>Magistrates</hi> in such cases act onely <hi>under him,</hi> and <hi>for him,</hi> and it is part of their office to take care that <hi>we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all Godliness and Honesty,</hi> which cannot be done without concerning themselves in matters of Religion. In short, <hi>Magistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> is the <hi>Ordinance</hi> and <hi>Institution</hi> of God, design'd for the good and benefit of the world, and therefore, is by no means vacated by our Saviour, nor can be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51733:9"/> while it keeps within its proper Sphere, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench upon any <hi>privilege</hi> or <hi>prerogative</hi> of his. But,</p>
            <p>Secondly, It follows farther from what has been said, <hi>that Kings derive not their power from the people;</hi> They are the <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> no <hi>Ordinance of man,</hi> their Lives and Beings are from God, and so is their Authority. In all the accounts we have in <hi>Scripture</hi> about <hi>Government,</hi> we shall find that God is princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally interested; All that the people were to doe, was to submit to the divine Order and Appointment. <hi>Thou shalt in any wise set him King over thee whom the Lord thy God shall chuse,</hi> Deut. 17.15. they were not to chuse for themselves, but rest satisfied with that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signation God would be pleased to make. The power is from <hi>God,</hi> and therefore solely at <hi>his</hi> disposal, not the <hi>peoples.</hi> He may indeed convey this <hi>power</hi> by what ways and means his providence sees fit, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he has done it by several ways; there are, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, <hi>Elective</hi> Kingdoms as well as <hi>Successive,</hi> but even in those places where there is an <hi>Election</hi> of the <hi>Supreme Magistrate,</hi> though he may be <hi>nominated</hi> by the <hi>people,</hi> yet he is <hi>authoriz'd</hi> by <hi>God;</hi> His Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is wholly owing to the divine providence. <hi>Nemo dat quod in se non habet,</hi> is a known Maxim, no body can bestow upon another, what he hath not himself; now the people never had <hi>Supreme Authority,</hi> were never inverted with the <hi>Power of the Sword,</hi> and for that reason could not confer it upon another; and therefore (as has been well remark'd) <hi>All the people can doe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Supreme pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Right.</note>
               <hi>is to hold forth the person to the power, if God have so in his providence order'd it, not give the power to the person;</hi> in short, they never had it themselves, and therefore were never in a capacity of transferring it over to another. If it be said that they had such a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51733:9"/> power, let them shew their <hi>Grant</hi> and produce their <hi>Letters Patents;</hi> Search all the <hi>Scriptures</hi> and most ancient <hi>Records,</hi> you shall not find the least footstep of it, nor so much as the least claim laid to it for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ages after the <hi>Creation.</hi> These latter ages indeed as being more quick-sighted than their great Grand-Fathers, have made some pretences to it: But the strongest Arguments they have hitherto found out to back their Cause, have been <hi>force</hi> and <hi>violence,</hi> all their Endeavours of Reason are weak and trifling, built upon <hi>false</hi> and <hi>precarious Hypotheses,</hi> and notorious mistakes about the <hi>Original of mankind,</hi> and <hi>the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision of the Earth amongst the Sons of Noah.</hi> They talk much of a <hi>Pact</hi> or <hi>Contract</hi> between Prince and people, and from thence would derive the <hi>Original of Government;</hi> But if you ask them, when, and where, and by whom, or how this <hi>Pact</hi> or <hi>Covenant</hi> was made or consented to, you will find them as silent, or at least speak as little to the purpose as the <hi>Man in the Moon.</hi> It is an easie matter to make <hi>suppositions,</hi> and draw up <hi>Schemes</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> but <hi>proof</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> is that we require, and when they produce this for the <hi>people,</hi> we will make court to the <hi>Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> and pay our obedience to the <hi>Rabble.</hi> And if men would be quiet till that be done, we need not fear but our Government will last as long as the Sun and Moon shall endure. Another thing they sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose in this Controversie, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>equality of all men by Nature,</hi> is a thing was never yet in the world, but contradicts plain <hi>matter of fact</hi> and the <hi>History</hi> of the <hi>original of Government;</hi> for there has been always an <hi>Inequality</hi> amongst men, and as we differ in strength and proportion or other <hi>Natural Abilities,</hi> so we do in reference to <hi>Authority and Subjection:</hi> Some are born to <hi>govern,</hi> and some are born to be <hi>governed,</hi> and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51733:10"/> that by the <hi>prime Laws of Nature</hi> antecedent to any <hi>positive Fact</hi> or <hi>Contract</hi> between the Governours and Governed: from all which it follows,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>That there can be no Escheat or forfeiture of this power to the people.</hi> For if the Prince did not derive it from the <hi>people,</hi> it can never return to <hi>them</hi> but to <hi>God</hi> who first gave it, to him it may be forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and he may as he sees fit take the forfeiture, and dispossess the greatest <hi>Monarchs</hi> of their thrones and lives. Thus he dealt with <hi>Saul,</hi> and several of the <hi>Jewish Kings;</hi> Nay there is no <hi>Nation</hi> in the world but what can make proof of this by their own <hi>Histories.</hi> But now though a <hi>Prince</hi> may lose his right in reference to God, yet he does not in reference to man, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have nothing to doe with him, he being <hi>God's immediate Officer</hi> and alone under his cognizance and disposal; and though now he be not particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly <hi>nominated</hi> from <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>anointed</hi> by a <hi>Prophet,</hi> yet his Right and Title may be as good as theirs was, and his person altogether as sacred and inviolable. So that however he acts, he is by virtue of the <hi>Imperial Law</hi> and <hi>prerogative of Princes</hi> no-ways accountable to the <hi>people,</hi> but to <hi>God</hi> alone, who invested him with this <hi>Sacred power and Authority.</hi> And indeed sad would be the case of <hi>Princes,</hi> were they subject to the power and correction of the <hi>Mobile,</hi> they would be onely <hi>Titular</hi> and <hi>Nominal</hi> Kings, reign by Courtesie, and be daily exposed to the Frenzy of the <hi>Multitude.</hi> If once the people come to be imposed upon (which is no difficult matter) by some design<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ambitious man, to believe, that their Prince is either unfit for <hi>Government,</hi> or does not govern <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Law,</hi> but goes about to invade their <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Properties,</hi> must not this upon every turn throw all things into Confusion? for the <hi>Commonalty</hi> are
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51733:10"/> Rash and Furious, seldom stay to consider things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be too late, but are hurried on by a kind of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Brutish Impetus</hi> and violence, many times to act the dismallest <hi>Tragedies</hi> that ever the Sun saw: for how many <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Great men</hi> have fallen a Sacrifice to the rage, fury, and inconsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derateness of the <hi>people?</hi> And how many <hi>Kingdoms</hi> have been involv'd in bloud and slaughter, till at length one party prevails to the Ruine and Slavery of all the rest? There cannot therefore be a more pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Maxim</hi> to the peace and tranquillity of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than this, <hi>That Kings receive their power from the people, and that in case of Male-administration they are accountable to the people, and may escheat and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit it into their hands.</hi> This is thought to be the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyest way to keep <hi>Princes</hi> in awe, and make them more just and regular in their <hi>Government;</hi> whereas it rather seems a likelier way to make them <hi>Tyrants,</hi> to disable the people and secure themselves in their <hi>Thrones</hi> and <hi>Dominions;</hi> for upon this supposition of the <hi>peoples power over them,</hi> they will still be jealous of them, and truely they have but reason, considering how uneasie most are under even <hi>the best of Governments,</hi> how ready every body is from the man in the <hi>Gold-chain</hi> to the man in the <hi>Stall,</hi> to find fault with the management of affairs, and how attentively they listen to, and reflect upon all the pretended <hi>Miscarriages</hi> of their <hi>Governours:</hi> So that if <hi>Princes</hi> would sit safe upon their <hi>Thrones,</hi> they have not much cause wholly to rely upon the uncertain humours of the <hi>Vulgar.</hi> Their best security is <hi>from God,</hi> from him they have received their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and <hi>to him alone</hi> they are <hi>accountable</hi> for the use of it; <hi>the peoples</hi> concern is to <hi>submit</hi> and <hi>obey,</hi> not <hi>question</hi> their <hi>Governours,</hi> for however they Govern, the power can never <hi>Escheat</hi> or fall into <hi>their</hi> hands,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51733:11"/> but onely into <hi>God</hi>'s, whose <hi>ordinance</hi> it is. And thus much may serve for the first General head, <hi>viz. the Original and Divinity of Government,</hi> I come now to the Second thing propos'd, and that was to explain to you the <hi>Doctrine of Non-Resistance, whosoever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth the power, resisteth the ordinance of God:</hi> and for this purpose I shall speak to these two <hi>propositions,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, <hi>That in no case we may resist;</hi> and yet,</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That in all cases we are not bound to obey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, <hi>That in no case it is lawfull to resist:</hi> here is no exception in the Text of any person or occasion, but <hi>whosoever resisteth shall receive to himself damnation;</hi> nor do we find in all the Bible, any cases wherein we are allow'd to <hi>resist</hi> or <hi>hostilely oppose</hi> our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; neither do we find any instance thereof in all the <hi>primitive</hi> times, when, if ever, one would have thought such a resistance might have been lawfull, the <hi>Government</hi> being so <hi>arbitrary</hi> and <hi>tyrannical,</hi> and the miseries the first Christians endur'd so <hi>barbarous</hi> and <hi>savage,</hi> and contrary to all the sense and pity of <hi>Humane Nature.</hi> No! the great doctrine of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel was <hi>taking up the Cross,</hi> not <hi>taking up arms;</hi> no such thing as a <hi>Conspiracy</hi> or <hi>Insurrection</hi> hath the least countenance in our Religion, for therein we are told to this purpose, <hi>that to rebell against our Sovereign, is to rebell against God himself,</hi> whose Ordinance he is, and whose Image and Superscription he bears. This is the avowed <hi>Doctrine of our Church,</hi> as may be found in the <hi>Homilies</hi> and other <hi>Monuments</hi> thereof; and our Law hath drawn up a <hi>Declaration</hi> for us particularly of the Clergy, wherein we assert it not to be lawfull <hi>upon any pretence whatever</hi> to take up arms against the King's person,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act for Ʋni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity.</hi> XIV. Car. 2.</note> or against those, who are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missionated by him. These are our Circumstances, and of these we have but too much reason to be put
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51733:11"/> in mind, there having been now of late three sorts of men especially, who have gone about to subvert this Doctrine: there are the <hi>Atheists,</hi> the <hi>Papists,</hi> and those that call themselves the <hi>True-Protestants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And First, For the <hi>Atheists,</hi> These men cannot cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be friends to the <hi>Government</hi> which is the <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God,</hi> who disown the <hi>being of God,</hi> and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Foundation of all Religion. <hi>Religion</hi> is the greatest security of the Prince, so that his Authority, where this is undermin'd will have but little force. It is not probable it should last much longer, than till these men can find an opportunity to justle him out of <hi>his Throne,</hi> as they have endeavour'd to do <hi>God</hi> himself out of <hi>his.</hi> To resist their <hi>Sovereign</hi> can be thought no crime by them, who dare oppose the <hi>great Sovereign</hi> of the world, and bid open defiance to the Universal <hi>Lord of all.</hi> All the <hi>obligations</hi> they can be suppos'd to have to be true to the <hi>Government</hi> are <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Self-preservation,</hi> so that where this <hi>fear</hi> ceases, and they think themselves able to grapple with their Superiours, the <hi>obligation</hi> ceases too, and what then should hinder them from violating all Law, and plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Crown on their own heads? And as for <hi>Self-preservation,</hi> if they apprehend any danger by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, this must supersede all other obligations whatsoever, that is, they may preserve themselves though it be with the ruine of all mankind: a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that must needs be destructive of Government and Humane Society, for under this pretence of <hi>self-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation,</hi> the greatest Villanies may be acted, and this <hi>Fundamental Law of Nature</hi> pleaded in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. In fine, the principles of these mens policy are wholly founded upon <hi>self-Interest</hi> without any respect to the <hi>Publick,</hi> or that <hi>Community</hi> wherein they live; Its no wonder then, there should be of this sort of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51733:12"/> men in the present <hi>Conspiracy,</hi> men of <hi>Atheistical</hi> principles, of the Spawn of that <hi>great Leviathan,</hi> who for many years together hath been playing in these our waters, infested this our Land with the most lewd and pernicious practices and opinions.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, There is also another sort of men who do but too nearly concur with these in their Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents about Resistance, and these are the <hi>Romanists.</hi> They do indeed believe and adore a God in <hi>Heaven,</hi> but then they have another upon <hi>Earth;</hi> I mean their <hi>Lord God the Pope.</hi> In him they place such a <hi>Pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> or fulness of <hi>power,</hi> that he can Excommunicate and depose Princes, absolve their Subjects from Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, and license them to resist, rebell, nay, and assassinate their Sovereign.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Sacrīs Minister.</hi> l. 1. cap. 4.</note>
               <hi>Duarenus</hi> tells us that it was determin'd by <hi>Clement the</hi> 5th. in a Council held at <hi>Vienna,</hi> that the <hi>Pope had power over all Emperours and Kings, and that whatever Authority or Majesty they had, did wholly depend upon the Church of Rome.</hi> And it is highly probable, that it was in token of this Superiority over all mankind, that it is noted in the book of the <hi>Sacred Ceremonies</hi> of that Church,<note place="margin">Sacrar. Ceremon. &amp; Rit. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. Eccl. <hi>Rom.</hi> l. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>286.</hi> Ed. <hi>Colon. Ag. 1572.</hi> onely at the reception of an Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, after the Emperour has kiss'd the Pope's hands and feet, the Pope rises a little towards him when he is to kiss his cheek.</note>
               <hi>Quod Pontifex Romanus nemini Reverentiam facit;</hi> That the Pope reverences no body, <hi>nemini mortalium,</hi> no man whatever. To this extravagant height is the pretended Successour of St. <hi>Peter</hi> arriv'd, he is so far from imitating our <hi>Saviour,</hi> whose Vicar he would be thought to be, or St. <hi>Peter,</hi> whom he would have the world to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve was his <hi>Predecessour,</hi> that he refuses to give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Caesar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caesar</hi>'s, and will submit himself to no <hi>ordinance of man,</hi> neither <hi>King</hi> nor <hi>other Governour,</hi> though their Authority have the stamp of God upon it as visible as that of the greatest <hi>Clergy-man.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51733:12"/>
            <p>There are indeed those amongst them, that would confine the exorbitant Power of this <hi>ancient Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> and bring it within the compass of <hi>things Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual,</hi> who yet do assert his power of dispensing with the Oaths and Obligations of Subjects in case the <hi>Prince</hi> be an <hi>Heretick,</hi> that is, according to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Dialect, not of their Communion; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly <hi>the Pope</hi> hath made use of this Authority. Thus he dealt but lately with our Glorious Queen <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> He Excommunicates her, absolves her Subjects from their Obedience, and as much as in him lay, arms them against her State, Dignity, and Life too. This <hi>Bull</hi> indeed, though it made a great <hi>noise,</hi> yet did little <hi>mischeif;</hi> for upon some experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the <hi>Papists</hi> finding themselves too weak, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow the <hi>Establish'd Government,</hi> it was desired that this <hi>Bull</hi> might be understood with some Latitude, so as not to oblige <hi>Them, as matters then stood;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cambden E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz. <hi>An.</hi> 1580.</note> that is to say, they were not then able to put it into Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. They will very plausibly tell you, that they are for obedience to Kings, nay, and that this obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is due <hi>jure Divino</hi> by a Divine Right (so <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Perron</hi>) but then they also tell you, that a <hi>King may cease to be a King,</hi> he may forfeit his Right to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, particularly in the case of <hi>Heresie,</hi> and then to resist him is no resisting of a King. But thanks be to God, this <hi>Sophistry</hi> cannot prevail upon us; The King cannot forfeit his <hi>Crown</hi> to any but to <hi>God, He</hi> gave it him, and upon his abuse thereof or otherwise <hi>He</hi> may resume it, none else can lay claim to any power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; so that it is <hi>God alone</hi> who must dissolve the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation between Prince and People; and till <hi>he</hi> be pleas'd to doe it, it is not for us to attempt to <hi>break their bands asunder, and cast away their Cords from us.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:51733:13"/>
            <p>Religion can be no pretence to justify Rebellion, because the obedience we owe to Princes is not for their <hi>Religion,</hi> but for their <hi>Dignity</hi> and <hi>Authority.</hi> I confess that when a Prince does maintain and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the true <hi>Religion,</hi> it is a farther Motive to obey him; but the principal ground of our Subjection is his being the <hi>ordinance of God,</hi> his having received his <hi>power from God.</hi> The Powers of the world, when the Apostles writ, were <hi>Heathen</hi> and <hi>Infidel,</hi> and yet they tell us, they were <hi>from God,</hi> and enjoyn o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and Submission to them, notwithstanding the diversity of their <hi>Belief</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> They had not yet learnt the <hi>Romish</hi> Doctrine, <hi>that Infidelity or He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie are sufficient to dispossess men of their rights,</hi> they knew nothing of <hi>Dominion being founded in Grace,</hi> nor ever endeavour'd to introduce their Religion into the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire</hi> by the <hi>Murther</hi> of the <hi>Emperour, slaughter</hi> of the <hi>Senate,</hi> and involving <hi>all</hi> in <hi>Bloud</hi> and <hi>Massacre.</hi> These were Doctrines not found out till about seven or eight hundred years ago; from which time they have been pleaded and practised too, as opportunity has offer'd it self. Our poor Nation has had sufficient experience thereof, but very lately God deliver'd us from one of their <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>Conspiracies,</hi> when lo! we had scarce taken breath, but we were assaulted from another Coast, by men who would be thought their greatest Enemies: and these are,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Such as call themselves the <hi>True-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants.</hi> I give not this name in scorn, but am heartily sorry, that any who go by that name, should ever have given occasion for what I am to say. But the matter of fact is plain, and not to be denyed, and to palliate their Crimes is to make our selves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessory. We have had, with sorrow and shame be it spoken, such amongst our selves, who have equall'd,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51733:13"/> if not outdone the very <hi>Jesuits</hi> in all their doctrines about Government; we have had those who have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted, and <hi>resisted unto Bloud,</hi> who have not onely <hi>speculatively</hi> but <hi>practically</hi> maintain'd all their <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Disloyalty and Rebellion.</hi> But thanks be to God, this is none of the true and right ancient <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Doctrine,</hi> though some of great note and place have but two much encourag'd it. The name of <hi>Protestant,</hi> however since abus'd and misappli'd, is no name of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> nor was taken up (as<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Particularly</hi> Florimundus Raemondus. <hi>de Origine Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seon.</hi> l. 3. cap. 7.</note> some of the <hi>Papists</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinuate) to <hi>protest</hi> against the <hi>Authority</hi> of <hi>Princes,</hi> but against a<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Viz.</hi> Of the Arch-Duke of <hi>Austria</hi> and other Catholick Princes in the Diet of <hi>Spire. Mezeray.</hi> An. <hi>1529.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>particular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the Papists,</hi> made in opposition to the <hi>Reformation:</hi> and in that sense we would have it understood; you must <hi>protest</hi> against <hi>Popery,</hi> but not against your <hi>Prince.</hi> Search all the <hi>Confessions</hi> of the <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> and you will find they have taken particular care about this business of <hi>Obedience</hi> to <hi>Magistrates:</hi> there is<note n="†" place="margin">Suevic <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession.</hi>
               </note> one <hi>Confession</hi> that reckons this Obedience <hi>inter primi ordinis bona opera,</hi> amongst good works of the highest degree; and yet it must be confest that there have been some <hi>particular men,</hi> who notwithstanding this have by their writings, if not practices loosen'd the nerves of Government, and given but too much countenance to <hi>Resistance</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion;</hi> amongst which <hi>Calvin</hi> is reckon'd for one, and a <hi>principal</hi> one too. He was certainly a man of vast parts, Learning and Industry, and upon these accounts of deserved esteem in all the reformed Churches, and therefore the more likely to doe hurt, if his Notions were not sound and orthodox; and it must be own'd that they were not in this matter, whilst he supposes such a power in the <hi>Inferiour Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate as to curb the Superiour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calvin. <hi>Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tut.</hi> l. 4. cap. 20. § 31.</note> though he brings it
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51733:14"/> in with a <hi>fortè: perchance</hi> says he, the <hi>three Estates in their solemn Assemblies may have such a power.</hi> But what he onely thus <hi>cunningly</hi> or cautiously suppos'd, has been improv'd so far, that it has had a <hi>fatal influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> over a great part of <hi>our Christendom.</hi> We have had books upon books writ to this purpose, that in case the <hi>Supreme Magistrate</hi> transgress his Duty, the <hi>Inferiour Magistrate</hi> may and <hi>ought to resist him;</hi> and in case both are negligent, <hi>the majority of the people</hi> hath power over both; and if these also prove defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, then are the <hi>Ministers</hi> to come in, and thunder out their Excommunications; they also, it seems, are to take care <hi>ne quid detrimenti Resp. capiat,</hi> that no damage accrue to the publick. Now these principles, whatever <hi>Authority</hi> they may vouch, are none of the <hi>Protestant Doctrine</hi> but perfect <hi>Popery;</hi> they are no part of the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> I am sure not of <hi>ours:</hi> for part, and a prime part of <hi>our Reformation,</hi> did consist in asserting to our Princes their <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Prerogatives,</hi> against the <hi>Papal</hi> and <hi>all Incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> whatever; in freeing them from Vassalage ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>Foreign</hi> or <hi>Domestick</hi> Usurpation, and fixing their Crown above the reach of or <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>People.</hi> We wish, we pray for <hi>good Princes,</hi> but if they should chance to prove <hi>bad,</hi> we think our selves oblig'd by the <hi>Laws</hi> of God and the Land, and by the <hi>principles of our Reformation,</hi> by no means to <hi>resist</hi> them. We dare not presume to <hi>stretch forth our hands against the Lord's anointed,</hi> for <hi>bad</hi> Kings as well as <hi>good</hi> are <hi>from God,</hi> and no resistance is allow'd to either. Neither the <hi>Inferiour Magistrate,</hi> nor the <hi>Majority of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> nor the <hi>Minister,</hi> nor the <hi>Pope</hi> have any power upon any pretence to call them to account, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend wholly upon God, and are the <hi>next</hi> to him in the world.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:51733:14"/>
            <p>But in reference to us of this Nation, it is said that our <hi>Government</hi> is a <hi>mixt Monarchy,</hi> and that there is a <hi>Co-ordination</hi> in it, so that in case our Rights be inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, we may resist, provided especially such in whose hands part of the Government is suppos'd to be lodg'd, do abet and lead us on. If by <hi>mixt Monarchy</hi> be meant a <hi>Limited Monarchy,</hi> no doubt but <hi>ours</hi> is <hi>such,</hi> for it is <hi>limited</hi> by the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>God and Nature;</hi> by the general <hi>principles of Equity and Justice;</hi> and our <hi>Princes</hi> have been pleas'd to limit themselves, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>descending to govern by such and such <hi>particular Rules.</hi> Thus indeed it is <hi>limited</hi> but not by any <hi>Co-ordination;</hi> We have solemnly swore by the <hi>Oath of Supremacy,</hi> that the King is our <hi>onely Supreme Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> which plainly excludes all <hi>Co-ordination,</hi> for if he be <hi>Supreme</hi> and <hi>onely Supreme,</hi> there are no others can challenge an <hi>Equality of power</hi> or <hi>Government</hi> with him, nor therefore have any thing to doe to <hi>Judge</hi> or <hi>resist</hi> him. O! that this Doctrine had been known and believ'd for some time ago, it would have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented a great deal of that bloud that hath been spilt in this Nation; and would to God that now at last, men would open their eyes, and embrace such prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples as are pure and peaceable, and no longer suffer themselves to be impos'd upon by restless and design<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men. Though they appear never so <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Religious,</hi> if they <hi>speak evil of Dignities,</hi> and tempt you to Scorn, and <hi>resist</hi> the <hi>Authority</hi> that is set over you, you ought to avoyd and abhor them as much, as if they tempted you to <hi>Drunkenness</hi> or <hi>Ʋncleanness,</hi> or any of the lewdest Vices of the profligatest part of mankind; For <hi>Resistance</hi> of our <hi>Sovereign</hi> is as expresly against the Laws of God as any of these, no pretence whatever will excuse it, but <hi>he that resisteth</hi> (whosoever he be) <hi>shall receive to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51733:15"/> damnation.</hi> Thus much for the first particular, <hi>That in no case we ought to resist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Though in <hi>no case</hi> we may <hi>resist,</hi> yet in <hi>all cases we are not bound to obey.</hi> Though we make the <hi>Magistrate</hi> to be the <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> yet we do not Seat him in the <hi>Throne of God,</hi> nor expect that an <hi>Ʋniversal Obedience</hi> should be given him, in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he may please to command, for he is a man as well as we, and liable to the like Infirmities as we are; He is obnoxious to Errour, Passion, Revenge and all the disorders of Humane Nature, as well as the meanest of his Subjects. And then indeed we might be justly counted <hi>Flatterers,</hi> should we encourage men to obey him under such Circumstances: Though <hi>Resistance</hi> can never be <hi>Lawfull,</hi> yet <hi>Non-obedience</hi> may, and become a <hi>Duty;</hi> for notwithstanding that we exalt <hi>Princes</hi> so <hi>High,</hi> as to be <hi>next to God,</hi> yet we make <hi>God</hi> still to be <hi>above them,</hi> so that whereever the Command of the Magistrate clashes and interferes with the Command of God, we are in that case to set it aside, and <hi>obey God rather than man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Minister</hi> is confessedly the <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> and yet if he propose to our belief or practice, what is false or prohibited, his Authority can lay no obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation upon us, but we may and ought to with-hold our selves from Assent or Action: of the same Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is the Authority of the Prince, if he enjoyns us any thing inconsistent with the will of God, we are dispenst with our Obedience to him, by that greater obligation we owe to the <hi>Supreme Prince of all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in this case we ought to observe these two Rules.</p>
            <p>First, <hi>That we be fully assur'd, that what he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands is contrary to the Law of God,</hi> and this <hi>Assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> ought not to be grounded upon fancy, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51733:15"/> Probability, long and uncertain Deductions, or the opinion of others, how <hi>Religious</hi> soever they may appear, but upon the <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>evident Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of God himself. We have a plain Command to obey the Higher Powers, and we ought to have as plain a Command to satisfy our own Consciences and the World, before we withdraw our Obedience. In things Dubious, the Authority of our Governours should go a great way, so far as to preponderate all the little scruples that may arise in our minds: For that is not properly a <hi>TENDER CONSCIENCE,</hi> that boggles and starts at shadows and Fantômes, the reflexions of Humour and fancy; but that is a truly <hi>TENDER CONSCIENCE,</hi> that is mighty care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, in the first place, of observing the <hi>great Laws</hi> of Religion; and these are <hi>Obedience to God,</hi> and <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to our Governours.</hi> It will by no means suffer some bye-Considerations to supersede our Duty to either.</p>
            <p>In fine there is a Duty to God, and a Duty to man, especially <hi>a man of Authority,</hi> and these ought not to cross or thwart one another: Our Duty to God does not hinder our Duty to man, nor should our Duty to man, encroach upon our Duty to God. If man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand any thing that God has forbidden, we are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd from Obedience, but then we ought to be <hi>sure,</hi> that God has forbid it: our Duty to the Magistrate being so plain, nothing but a <hi>plain prohibition</hi> from God will secure us, from being guilty of the breach thereof.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, Another Rule that ought to be observ'd in this case is, <hi>that supposing we are assur'd that we ought not in some particular Instances obey the orders of our Governours,</hi> yet <hi>when we withdraw our O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, it should be without Noise or Tumult,</hi> it should
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51733:16"/> be <hi>modestly</hi> and <hi>humbly,</hi> with expressions of Sorrow that we cannot comply with them in what they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of us. We must not make <hi>Satyrs</hi> and <hi>Invectives,</hi> be daily libelling the Government, and exposing it to the contempt of the <hi>Populace.</hi> We ought not to make <hi>combinations</hi> and <hi>meetings,</hi> in opposition or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance of the <hi>publick Establishment.</hi> For suppose there should be no actual design of Evil carri'd on in these <hi>meetings,</hi> yet they are but too apt to breed and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish Discontent and ill Humours against our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; for it is a shrewd Temptation for men not to think or speak over-kindly of them, by whom they are forc'd into such <hi>Clandestine Assemblies.</hi> And these have been all-along lookt upon as dangerous to a State, especially to a <hi>Monarchy:</hi> hence the <hi>Roman Emperours</hi> were so exceeding jealous of these <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of any <hi>Combinations</hi> or <hi>Sodalities</hi> of men amongst them. If therefore we must dissent, if the unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of our <hi>Education,</hi> or <hi>Complexion</hi> or <hi>Acquaintance,</hi> may have caus'd us to imbibe principles that are not allow'd of by our Governours; if we <hi>cannot</hi> lay them down, let us at least retain them to our selves, and not endeavour to make <hi>Proselytes</hi> and Parties to the disturbance of the Government; if the case should so fall out, that we must disobey our Prince, let us do it with all the Humility and Care imaginable; let us be the more diligent to obey him in other matters, <hi>as far as we possibly can;</hi> so to satisfy the world, that it is not <hi>Humour</hi> or <hi>Interest,</hi> or any <hi>external Considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> whatever, but the <hi>sole apprehension of our Duty to God,</hi> that keeps us from complying with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of our Superiours.</p>
            <p>But farther, as we must not, obey the Magistrate, if he commands us any thing contrary to the Laws of God, no more are we bound to obey him, if he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51733:16"/> any thing contrary to the <hi>Laws of Nature,</hi> the <hi>Dictates of Equity and Justice,</hi> and the <hi>Rules of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi> There is a vast difference between <hi>Non-obedience</hi> and <hi>Resistance,</hi> we must not obey our Prince if he should impose any thing ill upon us, yet we must by no means resist him; but, if it will not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise be, commit our cause to God, and patiently suffer. This is that we call <hi>PASSIVE OBEDIENCE,</hi> a Doctrine that has of late been ridicul'd and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to be hooted out of the world, as that which hath no foundation either in <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Religion;</hi> Nay, we are told that the promoters of it are guilty of little less than <hi>Treason,</hi> and those that practise it are <hi>Felo's de se,</hi> guilty of their own death. The opinion it seems of these is, that in case we be persecuted contrary to Law, it is lawfull to <hi>Resist;</hi> if indeed the Law be on the Prince's side, there and then alone we are under the obligations of <hi>Non-resistance.</hi> But whether it be by Law, or contrary to Law that we chance to be persecuted, does not in the least alter the case, and notwithstanding these mens endeavours, it is <hi>prayers and tears</hi> we must still stick to. <hi>To resist our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign is as much against the Law of the Land as any Persecution can be:</hi> And though Religion does not oblige us to lay down our Civil or Natural Rights, yet it hath no where given us leave to maintain them by force against our <hi>Lawfull Governour.</hi> The <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate</hi> is the <hi>ordinance of God,</hi> and if he should abuse the Power committed to him by God, though we are not in all things bound to obey, yet we are so far from being empower'd to <hi>resist,</hi> that even in this case, <hi>He that resisteth, shall receive to himself damnation.</hi> And this brings me to the,</p>
            <p>Third and last thing propos'd, and that was to shew <hi>the ill Consequences of resisting the POWER.</hi> Nothing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51733:17"/> less than <hi>Damnation</hi> is their due, that is the <hi>Pay</hi> they are certain to receive, and if they be willing to serve for such wages, much good may it do them, I hope you have a better sense of things, and are not willing to purchase <hi>Damnation</hi> upon such accounts. The <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> we translate <hi>Damnation,</hi> is often put to denote both Temporal and Eternal Judgments; and both these are the usual Consequences of Resistance. This Life and the other have declar'd their abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of such designs, and both worlds have been made the Scenes of their punishment. But to be more particular, let us consider the ill Consequences of Resistance;</p>
            <p>First, <hi>With reference to Bodies Politick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>With reference to particular persons,</hi> and that in regard of this Life and the next, their <hi>present Security</hi> and their <hi>future happiness.</hi> But,</p>
            <p>First, <hi>With reference to Bodies Politick.</hi> This Doctrine of Resistance is the greatest <hi>Incendiary</hi> in the world, the onelyest way to put all things into Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bustion, and fire even <hi>Marble Kingdoms;</hi> for if the people may upon any account resist their Governours, no doubt but they will upon every one plead the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and with or without reason be daily embroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Nation; and what can be expected should be the issue of such like giddy and tumultuous proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, but certain Ruine and Confusion? if the feet will rise up against the head, and spurn it of the shoulders, the whole body must needs fall and sink into its Grave and Tomb. <hi>Civil wars</hi> are of all others the most de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive of the Peace, and very being of that Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety wherein they are acted, and have usually been more <hi>bloody,</hi> as they have been more <hi>inhumane</hi> than any <hi>foreign force</hi> whatever. These sort of <hi>unnatural dissentions</hi> have laid desolate as many Countries as any
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51733:17"/>
               <hi>Hostile Invasion,</hi> they have made them at least a more easie conquest to such as would attempt them. And I beseech you, let it be remembred (for it is a certain truth,) that more bloud has been spilt, more men have lost their Lives and fortunes by <hi>Resistance,</hi> than by the most <hi>Tyrannical Government.</hi> The remedy has been found worse than the disease. A <hi>Tyrant</hi> may destroy a great many Lives, but <hi>Rebellion</hi> has done more; where one hath slain his thousands, the other hath slain its ten thousands; so that upon the very account of humane Policy, if we would consult the interest of the Kingdom, and the saving mens Lives, <hi>TYRANNY IS BETTER THAN RESISTANCE,</hi> this latter having usually more dismal effects than the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. It is observ'd to my hand,<note place="margin">Jovian. <hi>p.</hi> 261.</note>
               <hi>That in the late War more bloud was shed in one Battel, than in all the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannies and persecutions of the Nation since the conquest. And in the two Kingdoms there has been more Christian bloud shed in Rebellions since the Reformation by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended undertakers of defensive War, than throughout the whole Roman Empire in nine of the ten famous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutions.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hunt</hi> in his * <hi>Postscript,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 89, 90.</note> will by no means allow us to remember our late troubles, but on the <hi>Anniversary</hi> of our <hi>martyr'd Sovereign,</hi> and we are very much beholding to him, that we may at least <hi>once a year</hi> vent our Sorrows, and reflect on these things. Let me beg of you then to take his grant, and if not before, yet on that day consider the dismal Calamities that befell our Nation, and whether they were not owing to this Doctrine of Resistance. Had not men been wheedled into a belief that they might lawfully resist their Sovereign, we had not been har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rass'd by so long a War, nor groan'd under the weight of so much and so innocent bloud, <hi>which may God of his infinite mercy never lay to the charge of us or any of our posterity.</hi> But,</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:51733:18"/>
            <p>Secondly, Let us consider <hi>the ill Consequences of Resistance, with respect to particular persons,</hi> and that with reference to their <hi>present security and wellfare,</hi> and their <hi>future happiness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In reference to their present wellfare,</hi> nothing in the world can be found more hurtfull to it; for if we consider them as members of a Community, whatever is pernicious to that, must of necessity be pernicious to them too. When a Storm is rais'd, one may be overwhelm'd as well as another, when once the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is in arms, it will be no easie matter to persuade them to disband; they may seize upon me, or thee, or whoever comes next, be they friends or foes, and be as unmercifull to us as the bloudiest Tyrant. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider farther, how <hi>unsuccessfull</hi> such a Resistance of our Governours uses to be. There is a <hi>Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> that guards the Thrones and persons of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which is a greater security to them than the strongest <hi>Military Defence.</hi> This watches over them when they are asleep, supports them under the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of their Cares, and disappoints or confounds all the devices of their Enemies. The very thoughts and imaginations of evil are many times brought to light, and that by ways the most strange and unlikely. <hi>A Bird of the air may carry the voice, and that which has wings may tell the matter, Eccles.</hi> 10.20. There are a thousand various accidents, besides the <hi>general treachery of mankind,</hi> which may defeat all our designs, and bring us to publick shame, a <hi>Cart</hi> or a <hi>Scaffold.</hi> The man that intends to be a <hi>Traytor,</hi> must at the same time arm himself to suffer the tortures of Death, the abhorrence of all good men, nay, and of the very Rabble too. Those, who it may be would have applauded and <hi>ador'd</hi> him had he had Success, will be the first to <hi>Hiss</hi> and <hi>Scorn</hi> him off the Stage of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51733:18"/> World. He leaves indeed a name behind, but such as will render him infamous to future ages; his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory is branded, his posterity becomes odious, and he entails poverty and dishonour upon his childrens children.</p>
            <p>The first Rebellion we find upon Record in <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> is that of <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and no less than two hundred and fifty <hi>PRINCES OF THE ASSEMBLY, famous in their generation, men of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown, Numb.</hi> 16. They were disgusted with <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> their chief Governours in things Sacred and Civil, and had a design to depose them from their Government; but what was the event of this? they and their accomplices were <hi>miraculously</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy'd, partly <hi>by fire from the Lord,</hi> and partly by the <hi>earth</hi>'s <hi>opening and swallowing them up alive.</hi> By which signal Judgments, God did manifest to all the world the greatness of his wrath and anger against such attempts upon Authority, and has left it upon Record, to serve as an admonition even to <hi>us upon whom the ends of the world are come.</hi> Nor has the fate of <hi>Traytors</hi> and <hi>Rebels</hi> been much more favourable since, they seldom <hi>dying the common death of all men.</hi> But suppose they should escape here, and God for <hi>reasons of Wisdom</hi> known onely to himself, should suffer them to accomplish their designs, and go to their Graves in peace; yet there is no doubt but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a sincere and solemn Repentance, they shall be sure to smart for it hereafter, their punishment in the next world shall compensate for what they wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They that resist, shall receive to themselves Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Damnation</hi> is a terrible word, and a terrible thing too, it is the horrour of mankind, that which does the most startle and affright the world, and yet
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51733:19"/> no less a punishment shall be the reward of the <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor:</hi> nay, if we will be so curious as to enquire into the occasion of God's making a <hi>Hell,</hi> we shall find it was particularly made for <hi>Traytors. It was,</hi> says our Saviour, <hi>prepared for the Devil and his Angels, Matt.</hi> 25.41. and we know their Crime was <hi>high Treason</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> against their <hi>Sovereign Lord</hi> and <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour.</hi> So that this place of <hi>Torment,</hi> had its very O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal and beginning from <hi>Treason,</hi> and therefore is the fittest place for such as are guilty of it, and thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they must go to be company for those <hi>Revolted Spirits</hi> their fellow-<hi>Traitors.</hi> And indeed what Crime can deserve it more? they affront the most publick and visible Authority and Ordinance of God, they destroy the peace of mankind, and as much as in them lies, dissolve all into Bloud and Massacre. The greatest Thieves and Robbers, the most cruel <hi>Banditi</hi> are but puny Sinners compar'd to these; for they onely prey upon a <hi>few stragling particulars,</hi> but these set upon <hi>whole Communities,</hi> and are oftentimes the occasion of the slaughter of many <hi>thousands.</hi> A <hi>Seditious</hi> man is judg'd to be a greater enemy to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind than a <hi>Murtherer,</hi> for though the <hi>Murtherer</hi> may be suppos'd to have his hands dipt in the bloud of some, yet they cannot be many, whereas the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious</hi> man has his hands in the bloud of whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: and if to be the death or ruine of one man or family, be truely sentenc'd so horrid a Crime, much more must be the slaughter of vast Multitudes and the Ruine of Kingdoms. I wish to God, men would but seriously reflect on these things, it would sure make them lay their hands upon their hearts, and resolve if they have done wickedly, they will doe so no more; it would make them mighty carefull, how they as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perse their Governours, defame the Government,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51733:19"/> and thereby stir up the rage and violence of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, till at last, when it is too late to help it, they see themselves floating in a Sea of bloud, and the Ghost of the slaughter'd groaning out Curses, and calling for Vengeance upon them; which however it may miss them now, will certainly one day overtake them: then all their colours will fall off, their pleas be overrul'd, and they shall go naked and <hi>speechless</hi> into Hell. I must confess, this is a sad and sorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Subject, but it is <hi>true.</hi> Those indeed who have no sense of Religion, w'ont much value all this: but that men who <hi>pretend to Religion,</hi> and that in the <hi>greatest strictness and purity</hi> should not take notice of these things, would be to me wonder and Astonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but that I know that all that pretend to <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> are not <hi>Religious.</hi> A <hi>truly Religious</hi> man, one that has care of his own Salvation, should be sure in the first place to observe the <hi>great Commands</hi> of the Gospel, and those are <hi>to give obedience to God,</hi> and to <hi>our Governours,</hi> and that <hi>for the Lord's sake,</hi> not onely <hi>for wrath,</hi> but also <hi>for Conscience,</hi> considering that God has declar'd that the <hi>Magistrate</hi> is <hi>his Ordinance,</hi> and <hi>whosoever he be that resisteth, shall receive to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self Damnation.</hi> But to draw to a Conclusion,</p>
            <p>I have been speaking upon a Subject, that was but lately very unacceptable, but both then and now highly necessary, so that to have baulkt this especially at this time, would have been in a great measure to have baulkt my Duty, and the <hi>business of the day.</hi> We are enjoyn'd at this time, to commemorate and bless God for the deliverance of our King and Nation, from men of <hi>Rebellious</hi> and <hi>Antimonarchial</hi> principles, and I thought I could not better employ my self, than in representing the weakness, falseness and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs of them. And I now freely declare, that it is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51733:20"/> my Judgment, that the <hi>Pulpit</hi> ought to make satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to the <hi>Publick,</hi> for what the <hi>publick</hi> has suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the <hi>Pulpit.</hi> It was from thence that <hi>Guns</hi> have been discharg'd, <hi>Bombes</hi> and <hi>Granadoes</hi> thrown, that set on fire our whole Kingdom; and is it not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son <hi>we</hi> should now at last be suffer'd to bring water to quench these <hi>Flames?</hi> It is sure more consistent with the <hi>Ministery</hi> of the Gospel, which is a Gospel of Love and Peace, and Reconciliation, to preach us peaceable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and Submission, and dependence upon the Divine providence, than to beat the Drum, blow the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and alarum men into War and Rebellion. We have no Authority for such like <hi>Military</hi> proceedings, we are <hi>Embassadors of peace,</hi> not <hi>Heralds of Hostility,</hi> and herein we do but put in execution the Command given to us <hi>Clergy-men</hi> in the person of <hi>Titus</hi> who was a <hi>Clergy-man,</hi> i. e. <hi>to put you in mind to be subject to Principalities and Powers, to obey Magistrates and be ready to every good work. Tit.</hi> 3.1. And is there not cause to do this, and <hi>now</hi> more especially since the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of this <hi>HORRID CONSPIRACY,</hi> to secure men from the like practices for the future, which is one of the great ends of appointing this <hi>Festival,</hi> as also to bless and praise God for delivering us, and our King from the attempts of those Sons of Bloud and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence? Let thy name O Lord! endure for ever, and the memorial of this thy kindness throughout all Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations: We bless thee, we praise thee, we adore thee, that thou hast not given us <hi>as a prey to their teeth, but that our Soul is escaped as a Bird out of the Snare of the Fowlers, the Snare is broken and we are escap'd;</hi> But all we are to do on this day, does not consist in powring out our Souls in Hallelujahs and Songs of praise to God, but we must endeavour to impress upon our minds a greater sense of the <hi>Divine
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51733:20"/> Love,</hi> and a greater dependence upon the <hi>Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence;</hi> we must express our Thankfulness to God, by our Charity to the poor, which ought to be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant attendant upon every Festival; and by our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutions of a more carefull obedience <hi>to God</hi> and his <hi>Ordinance,</hi> I mean the King, than hitherto we have given them, not by prophaneness and Debauchery, Swearing and Intemperance, involving the Innocent with the Guilty, and a rude unmanly insulting over our Brethren; for by this means we shall onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the anger of God against us, and make him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of the good he has done for us, and at last after all our deliverances give us up to Ruine and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, which God of his great mercy prevent.</p>
            <p>I shall add no more, but desire you would seriously reflect upon what has been said, which I do assure you has not been with any design to <hi>please</hi> or <hi>displease</hi> one party of men or other amongst you, but to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the sense of my own Soul, and was really in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the good of yours.</p>
            <p>I shall therefore conclude all with that Collect af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Commandments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Almighty God whose Kingdom is everlasting and power infinite, have mercy upon the whole Church, and so rule the heart of thy chosen servant Charles our King and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, that he (KNOWING WHOSE MINISTER HE IS,) may above all things seek thy honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and that we and all his Subjects, (DƲLY CONSIDE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RING WHOSE AƲTHORITY HE HAS) may faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully serve, honour and humbly obey him, in thee and for thee ACCORDING TO THY BLESSED WORD AND ORDINANCE through Jesus Christ our Lord, who with thee and the Holy Ghost liveth and reigneth ever one God world without end.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>